Guide to the Lord Edward Pelham-Clinton papers, 1838-1907
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Lord Edward Pelham-Clinton papers 1838-1907
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Pelham-Clinton, Edward, Lord, 1836-1907
10 Linear Feet 53 Items
Lord Pelham-Clinton was the Groom-in-waiting and the Master of the Household to Queen Victoria.
Collection houses the papers of Lord Edward William Pelham-Clinton, including recollections of Queen Victoria and Edward VII, diaries, and autograph albums.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lord Edward Pelham-Clinton papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from 1985-1989.
Biographical Note
Lord Edward William Pelham-Clinton (August 11, 1836-July 9, 1907), after receiving his education at Eton, served in the military at Crimea, India and Canada, eventually reaching the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. From 1881 to 1894, Pelham-Clinton served as Groom-in-waiting to Queen Victoria. Consequently he acted as Master of the Household from 1894 until her death. Pelham-Clinton received two of the most top honors in Britain: Knight Commander of the Most Honourable Order of the Bath and Knight Grand Cross of the Royal Victorian Order.
Collection Overview
Collection houses the papers of Lord Edward William Pelham-Clinton, including recollections of Queen Victoria and Edward VII, diaries, and autograph albums.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Pelham-Clinton, Edward, Lord, 1836-1907
Edward VII, King of Great Britain, 1841-1910
Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, 1819-1901
Queens -- Great Britain
Royal households -- Great Britain -- Officials and employees
Great Britain -- History -- Victoria, 1837-1901
Great Britain -- Kings and rulers
Autograph albums
Diaries
Contents of Collection
- Lord Edward Pelham-Clinton papers, 1838-1907, (17 boxes)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1860-1895 (Box 1)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria and Edward VII, 1901-1903 (Box 2)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1879-1895 (Box 3)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1896-1898 (Box 4)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1899-1903 (Box 5)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1883-1897 (Box 6)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1899-1901 (Box 7)
  - H. Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1897-1907 (Box 8)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1887-1897 (Box 9)
  - 1895-1901 [Season Kalender] (Box 9)
  - Autograph album (Box 9)
  - Autographs-I (Box 10)
  - Autographs-II (Box 11)
  - Recollections of King Edward VII, 1903-1907 (Box 12)
  - Leaves From my Diary, 1901 Jan.-Feb. (Box 12)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1838-1895 (Box 13)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1895-1899 (Box 14)
  - Recollections of King Edward VII, 1900-1907 (Box 15)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1887-1902 (Box 16)
  - Recollections of Queen Victoria, 1900-1902 (Box 17)